Breaking up is hard to do – or so some people say.
分手总是令人难以释怀——至少有些人是这么说的。
If you’re in a relationship but not as loved-up as you once were, when is the right time to call it a day?
如果你正处于一段感情中，却早已不复往日的如胶似漆，那么何时才是结束这段关系的恰当时机？
The longer the relationship, the harder it can be.
感情持续得越久，抽身就可能越艰难。
But once you do make the break, is it still possible to maintain a friendship with your ex-partner?
但一旦你真的选择分手，还能和前任做朋友吗？
When you’ve been dumped, the classic line that’s often used is ‘let’s just be friends’.
当你被甩的时候，最常听到的经典台词就是“我们还是做朋友吧”。
That can be either wishful thinking or something to soften the blow of bad news.
这句话要么是一厢情愿的想法，要么就是用来缓和分手这个坏消息带来的打击。
However, when you fell madly in love with your partner all those weeks, months or years ago, it would have been hard to imagine you’d fall out of love.
然而，回想数周、数月乃至数年前，你曾和对方爱得轰轰烈烈，那时的你大概怎么也想不到，自己有一天会失恋。
And so salvaging something from that time, and remaining friends, could be a good thing to do.
如此说来，从这段逝去的感情里挽回些什么，和对方做朋友，或许也是一件好事。
It’s good if a break-up is amicable – it avoids the hate, pain and anger that can eat away at us and affect our mental health.
如果分手能好聚好散，那自然再好不过——这样就可以避免那些会侵蚀我们内心、影响心理健康的怨恨、痛苦和愤怒。
If you can accept you’ve had some good times but it’s time to move on, then all the better – besides, you won’t have to cancel your ex-partner from social media or delete their name from your contacts!
要是你能坦然接受彼此曾拥有过美好时光，但如今已到了该各自前行的时刻，那就更好了——而且你也不用把前任从社交媒体上拉黑，或是在通讯录里删除对方的名字！
If you can appreciate the mutual interests you had then there’s no reason why you can’t continue a platonic relationship.
如果你们还能欣赏彼此共同的兴趣爱好，那么维持一段柏拉图式的友谊也未尝不可。
But holding onto the past and staying friends doesn’t always work – you just have to accept you and your partner just weren’t compatible, therefore it’s best to give each other space, to look forward, and try to get any romantic feelings you once had out of your system.
但沉湎过去、成为彼此的朋友，并非总能行得通——你不得不承认，你和对方终究是不合适的。因此，最好的做法是给彼此留出空间，向前看，并努力放下曾经的爱恋之情。
And according to some, staying friends with your ex isn’t a good option.
在有些人看来，和前任做朋友并非明智之选。
Marie-Claire Chappet told the BBC, “It does nothing but prolong the pain of the break-up”.
玛丽-克莱尔·沙佩告诉英国广播公司：“这样做只会延长分手后的痛苦。”
Helen Fisher, a neurologist at the Kinsey Institute who’s been studying the psychology in relationships, also told the BBC: “The way to accelerate mending a broken heart is similar to treating addiction – you put away their things, stop looking at their social media and have no contact with them.”
金赛研究所的神经学家海伦·费舍尔一直在研究两性关系心理学，她也向英国广播公司表示：“治愈破碎的心，方法和戒除毒瘾有异曲同工之妙——把对方的东西收起来，不再浏览他们的社交媒体，和对方彻底断绝联系。”
So, maybe it’s time to get in touch with your real friends, instead of seeking friendship with ‘a ghost from the past’.
所以，或许你该做的是联系自己真正的朋友，而不是试图和“过去的影子”做朋友。